Off to the fair.
The night before the county fair, everybody went to bed early. Fern and
Avery were in bed by 8.
Avery lay dreaming that the ferris wheel had stopped and that he was in the top
car. Fern lay dreaming that she was getting sick in the swings.
Larvy was in bed by 8:30. He lay dreaming that he was throwing baseballs
at a cloth cat and winning a genuine Navajo blanket.
Mr. and Mrs. Zuckerman were in bed by 9.
Mrs. Zuckerman lay dreaming about a deep freeze unit. Mr. Zuckerman lay dreaming about Wilbur.
He dreamt that Wilbur had grown until he was 116 ft long and 92 feet high, and
that he had won all the prizes at the fair and was covered with blue ribbons
and even had a blue ribbon tied to the end of his tail.
Down in the barn cellar, the animals too went to sleep early. All except
Charlotte. Tomorrow would be fair day.
Every creature planned to get up early to see Wilbur off on his great
adventure. When morning came, everybody got up at daylight. The day was hot. Up
the road at the Arable's house, Fern lugged a pale of hot water to her room
and took a sponge bath.
Then she put on her prettiest dress because she knew she would see boys at
the fair. Mrs. Arable scrubbed the back of Avery's neck and wet his hair and
parted it and brushed it down hard till it stuck to the top of his head. All but
about six hairs that stood straight up.
Avery put on clean underwear, clean blue jeans, and a clean shirt.
Mr. wearable dressed, ate breakfast, and then went out and polished his truck. He
had offered to drive everybody to the fair, including Wilbur.
Bright and early, Lurvy put clean straw in Wilbur's crate and lifted it into the
pig pin. The crate was green. In gold letters, it said, "Zuckerman's famous pig."
Charlotte had her web looking fine for the occasion. Will ber ate his breakfast
slowly. He tried to look radiant without getting food in his ears.
In the kitchen, Mrs. Zuckerman suddenly made an announcement. Homer, she said to
her husband, I am going to give that pig a buttermilk bath.
What? said Mr. Zuckerman. A buttermilk bath. My grandmother used to bathe her
pig with buttermilk when it got dirty. I just remembered.
Wilbur's not dirty, said Mr. Zuckerman proudly.
He's filthy behind the ears, said Mrs.
Zuckerman. Every time Lurvy slops him, the food runs down around the ears. Then
it dries and forms a crust. He also has a smudge on one side where he lays in
the manure.
He lays in clean straw, corrected Mr.
Zuckerman.
Well, he's dirty and he's going to have a bath. Mr. Zuckerman sat down weakly
and ate a donut.
His wife went to the woodshed. When she returned, she wore rubber boots and an
old raincoat, and she carried a bucket of buttermilk and a small wooden paddle.
You're crazy," mumbled Zuckerman.
But she paid no attention to him.
Together, they walked to the pig pin.
Mrs. Zuckerman wasted no time. She climbed in with Wilbur and went to work.
Dipping her paddle in the buttermilk, she rubbed him all over. The geese
gathered around to see the fun, and so did the sheep and lambs. Even Templeton
poked his head out cautiously to watch Wilbur get a buttermilk bath. Charlotte
got so interested she lowered herself on a drag line so she could see better.
Wilbur stood still and closed his eyes.
He could feel the buttermilk trickling down his sides.
He opened his mouth and some buttermilk ran in. It was delicious.
He felt radiant and happy when Mrs.
Zuckermanman got through and rubbed him dry. He was the cleanest, prettiest pig you ever saw.
He was pure white, pink around the ears and snout, and smooth as silk. The
Zuckermanman's went up to change into their best clothes. Lurvy went to shave
and put on his plaid shirt and his purple necktie. The animals were left to
themselves in the barn.
The seven gosslings paraded round and round their mother. "Please, please,
please take us to the fair," begged a gozling. Then all seven began teasing to
go. "Please, please, please, please." They made quite a racket. Children,
snapped the goose. We're staying quietly idly, idly at home. Only Wilbury Il is
going to the fair.
Just then, Charlotte interrupted. I shall go too, she said softly. I have
decided to go with Wilbur. He may need me. We can't tell what may happen at the fairgrounds.
Somebody's got to go along who knows how to write, and I think Templeton better
come, too. I might need somebody to run errands and do general work.
I'm staying right here, grumbled the rat. I haven't the slightest interest in
fairs. That's because you've never been to one, remarked the old sheep. A fair
is a rat's paradise.
Everybody spills food at a fair. A rat can creep out late at night and have a
feast. In the horse barn, you will find oats that the trotters and paces have spilled.
In the trampled grass of the infield, you will find old discarded lunchboxes
containing the foul remains of peanut butter sandwiches, hardboiled eggs,
cracker crumbs, bits of donuts, and particles of cheese.
In the hard pack dirt of the midway, after the glaring lights are out and the
people have gone home to bed, you will find a veritable treasure of popcorn
fragments, frozen custard ribblings, candid apples abandoned by tired
children, sugar fluff crystals, salted almonds, popsicles, partially gnawed ice
cream cones, and the wooden sticks of lollipops. S everywhere is loot for a rat in tents
and booths and hoffs. Why a fair has enough disgusting leftover food to
satisfy a whole army of rats.
Templeton's eyes were blazing. "Is this true?" he asked. "Is this uh appetizing
ya yours true? I like high living and what you say pimps me.
It is true, said the old sheep. Go to the fair, Templeton. You will find that
the conditions at a fair will surpass your wildest dreams.
Buckets with sour mash sticking to them.
Tin cans containing particles of tuna fish. Reeseasy paper bag stuffed with
rotten "That's enough," cried Templeton.
"Don't tell me anymore. I'm going."
"Good," said Charlotte, winking at the old sheep.
"Now then, there is no time to be lost.
Wilbur will soon be put into the crate.
Templeton and I must get in the crate right now and hide ourselves." The rat
didn't waste a minute. He scampered over to the crate, crawled between the slats,
and pulled straw up over him so he was hidden from sight.
"All right," said Charlotte. "I'm next."
She sailed into the air, let out a drag line, and dropped gently to the ground.
Then she climbed the side of the crate, and hid herself inside a knot hole in
the top board. The old sheep nodded.
What a cargo. She said that sign ought to say Zuckerman's famous pig and two stowways.
Look out.
The people are coming.
Shouted the gander. Cheese it, cheese it, cheese it. The big truck with Mr.
Rarable at the wheel back slowly down toward the barnyard. Lurvy and Mr.
Zuckerman walked alongside. Fern and Avery were standing in the body of the
truck, hanging on to the sideboards.
"Listen to me," whispered the old sheep to Wilbur. "When they open the crate and
try to put you in, struggle. Don't go without a tussle. Pigs always resist
when they are being loaded." "If I struggle, I'll get dirty," said Wilbur.
Never mind that. Do as I say, struggle.
If you were to walk into the crate without resisting, Zuckerman might think
you were bewitched. He'd be scared to go to the fair.
Templeton poked his head up through the straw. Struggle if you must, he said.
But kindly remember that I'm hiding down here in this crate and I don't want to
be stepped on or kicked in the face or pummeled or crushed in any way or
squashed or buffeted about or bruised or lacerated or scarred or biffed.
Just watch what you're doing, Mr.
Radiant, when they get shoving you in.
Be quiet, Templeton, said the sheep.
Pull in your head. They're coming. Look, Ray and Wilbur. Lay low, Charlotte. Talk
it up, geese. The truck back slowly to the pig pin, and stopped. Mr. Arable cut
the motor, got out, walked around to the rear, and lowered the tailgate. The geese cheered.
Mrs. Arable got out of the truck. Fern and Avery jumped to the ground. Mrs.
Zuckerman came walking down from the house.
Everybody lined up at the fence and stood for a moment, admiring Wilbur and
the beautiful green crate. Nobody realized that the crate already contained a rat and a spider.
"That's some pig," said Mrs. Arable.
"He's terrific," said Lurvy. He's very radiant, said Fern, remembering the day
he was born. Well, said Mrs. Zuckerman, he's clean anyway. The buttermilk certainly helped.
Mr. Arable studied Wilbur carefully.
Yes, he's a wonderful pig, he said. It's hard to believe that he was the runt of
the litter. You'll get some extra good ham and bacon, Homer, when it comes time
to kill that pig.
Wilbur heard these words and his heart almost stopped. "I think I'm going to
faint," he whispered to the old sheep who was watching.
"Nelle down," whispered the old sheep.
"Let the blood rush to your head."
Wilbur sank to his knees, all radiance gone. His eyes closed. "Look!" screamed
Fern. He's fading away. Hey, watch me, yelled Avery, crawling on all fours into
the crate. I'm a pig. I'm a pig. Aver's foot touched Templeton under the straw.
What a mess, thought the rat. What fantastic creatures boys are. Why did I
let myself in for this?
The geese saw Avery in the crate and cheered.
Avery, you get out of that crate this instant, commanded his mother. What do
you think you are? I'm a pig, cried Avery, tossing handfuls of straw into the air.
The truck is rolling away, Papa said Fern. The truck, with no one at the
wheel, had started to roll downhill.
Mr. Arable dashed to the driver's seat and pulled on the emergency brake. The
truck stopped. The geese cheered.
Charlotte crouched and made herself as small as possible in the knot hole so
Avery wouldn't see her. "Come out at once!" cried Mrs. Herble. Avery crawled
out of the crate on hands and knees, making faces at Wilbur. Wilbur fainted away.
"The pig has passed out," said Mrs.
Zuckerman. Throw water on him. Throw buttermilk, suggested Avery. The geese cheered.
Lurvy ran for a pale of water. Fern climbed into the pin and knelt by
Wilbur's side. It's Sunstroke, said Zuckerman. The heat is too much for him.
Maybe he's dead, said Avery.
Come out of that pig pin immediately," cried Mrs. Arable. Avery obeyed his
mother and climbed into the back of the truck so he could see better. Lurvy
returned with cold water and dashed it on Wilbur.
"Throw some on me!" cried Avery. "I'm hot, too." "Oh, keep quiet!" hollered
Fern. "Keep quiet!" Her eyes were brimming with tears. Wilbur, feeling the
cold water, came too. He rose slowly to his feet while the geese cheered.
"He's up," said Mr. Arable. "I guess there's nothing wrong with him." "I'm
hungry," said Avery. "I want a candied apple."
"Wilbur's all right now," said Fern. "We can start. I want to take a ride in the
ferris wheel." Mr. Zuckerman and Mr.
Ariel and Lervy grabbed the pig and pushed him headfirst toward the crate.
Wilbur began to struggle. The harder the men pushed, the harder he held back.
Avery jumped down and joined the men.
Wilbur kicked and thrashed and grunted.
"Nothing wrong with this pig," said Mr.
Zuckerman cheerfully, pressing his knees against Wilbur's behind. All together now, boys. Shove.
With a final heave, they jammed him into the crate. The geese cheered.
Lurvy nailed some boards across the end so Wilbur couldn't back out. Then, using
all their strength, the men picked up the crate and heaved it aboard the truck.
They did not know that under the straw was a rat and inside a knot hole was a
big gray spider. They saw only a pig.
"Everybody in," called Mr. Arable. He started the motor. The ladies climbed in
beside him. Mr. Zuckerman and Lurvy and Fern and Avery rode in back, hanging on
to the sideboards. The truck began to move ahead. The geese cheered.
The children answered their cheer.
Woohoo! Woohoo! And away went everybody to the fair.
[Music]